Register of the Charles Kendrick papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Charles Kendrick papers
1915-1972
83041
Hoover Institution Archives
8 manuscript boxes (3.2 linear feet)
Speeches, correspondence, diaries, minutes, reports, memoranda, maps, orders, photographs, and memorabilia, relating to American military activities in France during World War I, Herbert Hoover, national business associations in the United States, and San Francisco civic affairs.
Kendrick, Charles, 1876-1970.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1983.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1876 Born in San Francisco
1898-1901 Attended Kent Law School
1902 Admitted to the Bar
1917-1918 Served in World War I
1920-1938 Served as a trustee of the San Francisco War Memorial
1923-1926 Served as a member of the Advisory Committee for the San Francisco Water System
1924-1930 Served as a member of the San Francisco Planning Commission
1932-1934 Served as a member of the San Francisco Relief Committee
1938-1940 Served as Vice President of the Golden Gate International Exposition
1943-1946 Served as President of the Board of Trustees for Mills College
1942-1943 Served as President of the Pan America Union
1926-1969 Worked for the Schlage Lock Company, from temporary management to President to Chairman of the Board
1976 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
Speeches, correspondence, reports, diaries, minutes, photographs, memoranda, newspaper articles, pamphlets, printed media, and other documents relating to the activities of the Bohemian Club, the Pan American Union, San Francisco civic affairs such as the San Francisco War Memorial and the Golden Gate International Exposition, World War I, and various national business associations. Also includes information on the establishment of the Hoover Institution and correspondence with Herbert Hoover, Richard Nixon, and Calvin Coolidge.
Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964.; United States. Army. American Expeditionary Forces.; San Francisco (Calif.); United States--Industries.; World War, 1914-1918--Campaigns--France.
- Biographical File, 1930-1966 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Photographs, programs, invitations, and other documents relating to the affairs of Charles Kendrick.
- Correspondence, 1915-1969
  General letters, telegrams, and other forms of correspondence to, from, and concerning Charles Kendrick and his affairs.
  - General, 1915-1969
    General correspondence, organized alphabetically by last name.
    - A-L, 1915-1969 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    - M-R, 1915-1969 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    - S-Y, 1915-1969 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Calvin Coolidge, 1924 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Count de la Gardie, 1949 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Family, 1932-1959 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Robert Jackson, 1949 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Richard Nixon, 1966-1969 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Nelson A. Rockefeller, 1945-1946 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - James Rolph, 1926-1930 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Thomas Sellers, 1950 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - Robert Stettinius, 1945 (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - Earl Warren, 1942 (Box-folder 1: 14)
  - Shigeru Yoshida, 1952 (Box-folder 1: 15)
- Speeches and Writings, 1920-1969
  Speeches, essays, notes, poems, and other writings authored by Charles Kendrick or used in his writings.
  - Russia, 1959-1961
    - Biography, 1961 (Box-folder 1: 16)
    - Russia, undated (Box-folder 1: 16)
    - Russia, drafts and notes, 1959 (Box-folder 1: 16)
    - Russia, final draft, 1959 (Box-folder 1: 16)
    - Russia, final report, undated (Box-folder 1: 16)
  - Pan American Union, 1930-1945
    - Anniversary Ceremony, Pan American Union, 1942 (Box-folder 1: 17)
    - Co-Operation with the Americas, 1943 (Box-folder 1: 17)
    - English Speaking Union, 1945 (Box-folder 1: 17)
    - Gold Medal, Pan American Society, 1944 (Box-folder 1: 17)
    - Latin American Co-Operation, 1942 (Box-folder 1: 17)
    - Luncheon in Honor of His Excellency Anastasio Somosa, President of the Republic of Nicaragua, 1939 (Box-folder 1: 17)
    - On Radio, Birthday of Bolivian Republic, 1942 (Box-folder 1: 17)
    - Untitled, undated (Box-folder 1: 17)
      Pan American Union related.
  - Golden Gate International Exposition, 1937-1939
    - Dedication of the French Pavilion, Golden Gate International Exposition, 1939 (Box-folder 1: 17)
    - Luncheon for the British Group, Golden Gate Exposition, 1938 (Box-folder 1: 17)
    - Luncheon in Honor of the Crown Prince and Crown Princess of Denmark, Treasure Island, 1939 (Box-folder 1: 17)
    - Luncheon in Honor of Herbert Hoover, Golden Gate International Exposition, 1939 (Box-folder 1: 17)
    - Opening of Golden Gate International Exposition on Treasure Island, 1937 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - Schools, 1921-1961
    - Commencement Address, University of San Francisco, 1961 (Box-folder 1: 17)
    - Convention of California School Superintendents, 1921 (Box-folder 1: 17)
    - Dedication of Vallejo High School, 1922 (Box-folder 1: 17)
    - Fall of Bastille Education, 1933 (Box-folder 1: 17)
    - Galileo High School, 1923 (Box-folder 1: 17)
    - Lincoln School Annual Dinner, 1939 (Box-folder 1: 17)
    - Lincoln School Annual Dinner Exposition, 1940 (Box-folder 1: 17)
    - Memoranda for speech made at Lincoln School Association, 1922 (Box-folder 1: 17)
    - Mills College, 1943 (Box-folder 1: 17)
    - Parent Teachers Association, Grant School, 1926 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - Commonwealth Club, 1926-1944
    - Commonwealth Club, Section on City Planning, 1926 (Box-folder 1: 18)
    - KLX Radio, Commonwealth Club, 1944 (Box-folder 1: 18)
    - Memo for address: "Recognition of Spain by United States,", 1950 (Box-folder 1: 18)
  - Off Night Club, 1926-1941
    - The Business of Distribution, 1930 (Box-folder 1: 18)
    - January 1926 (Box-folder 1: 18)
    - Looking Forward, 1934 (Box-folder 1: 18)
    - May 1941 (Box-folder 1: 18)
    - October 1928 (Box-folder 1: 18)
    - Preserving America's Self Respect, 1932 (Box-folder 1: 18)
    - Report on Trip to Mexico, 1930 (Box-folder 1: 18)
    - Tariffs, Their Uses and Abuses, 1936 (Box-folder 1: 18)
  - South of Market Boys, 1925-1926
    - An Organization Built on Sentiment, 1925 (Box-folder 1: 19)
    - Fathers and Sons Night, 1926 (Box-folder 1: 19)
    - KPO for South of Market Boys, 1925 (Box-folder 1: 19)
    - South of Market Boys' Association, Lincoln's Birthday, 1925 (Box-folder 1: 19)
    - South of Market Boys' Grand Ball, 1926 (Box-folder 1: 19)
  - War, peace, and patriotism, 1920-1950
    - Americanism, copy 1-2, 1924 (Box-folder 1: 19)
    - Armistice Celebration, San Francisco Elks, 1924 (Box-folder 1: 19)
    - Armistice Day at Santa Rosa, undated (Box-folder 1: 19)
    - Armistice Night Dinner, 1922 (Box-folder 1: 19)
    - Big War Memorial Drive, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 19)
    - Can We Have Peace?, 1945 (Box-folder 1: 19)
    - Fall of the Bastille, 1923 (Box-folder 1: 19)
    - Funeral oration over remains of Chinese veteran of Argonne, 1921 (Box-folder 1: 19)
    - General Sommerall, notes made on the scene, undated (Box-folder 1: 19)
    - Independence Day oration, 1922 (Box-folder 1: 19)
    - The New Freedom, 1930 (Box-folder 1: 19)
    - Postwar Alliances, 1943 (Box-folder 1: 19)
    - The Postwar Outlook, 1943 (Box-folder 1: 19)
    - Remarks prepared for burial of unknown dead at Arlington Cemetery, undated (Box-folder 1: 19)
    - Unknown dead soldier ceremony, 1921 (Box-folder 1: 19)
    - Untitled, undated (Box-folder 1: 19)
      Essay on the New Deal and dictatorship.
    - Whither Are We Drifting?, 1946
  - American Legion, 1920-1923
    - Highlights of the Legion National Convention, 1922 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Legion Convention of Kansas City, 1921 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Legion National Convention, 1923 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Legion National Convention, Chamber of Commerce, 1923 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Public meeting under auspices of American Legion, 1920 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Politics and the Republican National Convention, 1926-1965
    - Committee of Congressmen luncheon, 1935 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Convention Dinner of Delegates, Republican National Convention, 1940 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Definite Conclusions Reached by Me, Before Lunch with President Eisenhower, 1954 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Herbert Hoover, 1965 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Hoover and the Republican Convention at Philadelphia, 1940 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Meeting of Delegates, Republican National Convention, 1940 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Community Chest, 1923-1936
    - Community Chest, 1923 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Community Chest Campaign Luncheon, 1924 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Community Chest Luncheon, 1925 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Community Chest Luncheon, 13th Anniversary, 1936 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Memoranda for Community Chest Luncheon, 1936 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Addresses to Organizations and Groups, 1920-1942
    - Address to 300 newly naturalized citizens in Rotunda of City Hall, San Francisco, 1921 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Address to Utah Convention, 1922 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Bridge opening, 1936 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Convention of Combined Merced County Posts, 1920 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Examiner and Hale Bros, 1924 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Examiner Radio, 1924 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Ford Society Dinner, 1935 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Good Cheer Club, 1921 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Ground Breaking for St. Joseph's Hospital, 1926 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Luncheon of French Trade Commission, 1939 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Luncheon at Moore Drydock and Shipbuilding Companies, Launching of the Ship "Sea Arrow,", 1939 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Outline for talk given at Hollister, 1922 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Radio at Examiner and Hale Bros, 1924 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Remarks on the radio, 1942 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Rotary Club, 1932 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - State Convention, Women's Auxiliary, 1921 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Transcript from convention, 1923 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - San Francisco War Memorial, 1928-1962
    - Chronology: History of San Francisco War Memorial, 1933 (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - History of the War Memorial, 1962 (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - Untitled, 1928 (Box-folder 2: 2)
      Pertains to San Francisco War Memorial.
  - Addresses to people, 1920-1955
    - Address of Welcome to General Pershing, 1920 (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - Address to King and Queen of Greece, undated (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - Banquet for Marshal Foch, 1921 (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - Bier of Raymond Reubens, 1920 (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - Bust of Will Crocker, 1938 (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - Coolidge luncheon, 1924 (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - Dedication of Bust of Senator Phelan, 1951 (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - Dedication of Monument to Raphael Weill, 1925 (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - Gabriel Moulin, 1938 (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - George Bernard Shaw, undated (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - Luncheon for Crown Prince Olav and Crown Princess Martha, 1939 (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - Luncheon for Haig Patigian, 1938 (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - Luncheon in Honor of Governor Raymond Baldwin of Connecticut, 1939 (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - Luncheon for Miss Minerva Bernardino, 1944 (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - Memorial service for Frank Wentworth, 1955 (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - Padilla, undated (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - Remarks to Senator Phelan, 1937 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - Museums and the Arts, 1926-1939
    - Dinner of American Association of Museums, 1939 (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - Grand Opera performance, 1927 (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - Grand Opera performance, undated (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - Memo for Opera Season address, 1926 (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - Museum Directors Exposition, 1938 (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - Music, undated (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - National Meeting of Museum Directors and Curators, 1939 (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - Negro-minstrelsy, undated (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - Notes for possible address at the opening of the Opera, 1932 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Notes, memos, and miscellaneous writings, 1924-1968
    - Citation for Charles Kendrick, undated (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - Grove memo, 1951 (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - In commemoration of Kendrick Hall, 1962 (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - India House, 1952 (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - Stray thoughts, undated (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - Material developed, not used, undated (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - Memos, undated (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - Notes, undated (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - Prominent men of San Francisco, 1924 (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - Report on trip made at 2701 Prince, undated (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - Riding for health, 1927 (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - Untitled, 1968 (Box-folder 2: 3)
      Pertains to Alfred Wright, Jr.
  - Bohemian Club, 1925-1955
    - A Salute to Lady Isis, 1944 (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - A Satire on the Jinks Committee, 1938 (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - Annual Dinner, Bohemian Club Orchestra, 1937 (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - Archaeology and the Bible, 1955 (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - The Bible, 1952 (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - Bohemian Club, 1933 (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - Bohemian Club Chorus Dinner, 1937 (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - Bohemia Honors Her First Flute, 1941 (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - Chairs' Dinner, 1938 (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - Christmas, 1936-1943
      - Christmas Dinner, 1943 (Box-folder 2: 4)
      - Christmas Dinner, Bohemian Club, 1943 (Box-folder 2: 4)
      - Christmas Jinks, 1936 (Box-folder 2: 4)
      - Christmas Jinks, Bohemian Club, 1937 (Box-folder 2: 4)
      - Christmas Jinks Introductions, 1937 (Box-folder 2: 4)
      - Christmas Jinks Pamphlet, 1936 (Box-folder 2: 4)
      - Christmas Jinks Pamphlet, 1937 (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - Dinner in Honor of Herbert Hoover, Bohemian Club: Introduction, 1938 (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - Ladies' Night, Orchestra Night, 1927 (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - Ladies' Night in Bohemia, Orchestra Concert, 1947 (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - Old Guard Dinners, 1937-1954
      - 1937 (Box-folder 2: 4)
      - Speeches 1-3, 1938 (Box-folder 2: 4)
      - Speeches 1-3, 1954 (Box-folder 2: 4)
      - Notes for Old Guard speech, undated (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - President's Dinner, 1927-1938
      - 1927 (Box-folder 2: 4)
      - 1936 (Box-folder 2: 4)
      - 1937 (Box-folder 2: 4)
      - 1938 (Box-folder 2: 4)
      - Call to President's Dinner, 1927 (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - Thanksgiving, 1951
      - Notes for Thanksgiving Night speech, 1951 (Box-folder 2: 4)
      - Thanksgiving Night, Bohemian Club, 1951 (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - Untitled, 1950 (Box-folder 2: 4)
- Miscellaneous, 1923-1968 (Box-folder 2: 5-7, Box-folder 3: 1-2)
  Pamphlets, invitations, booklets, newspaper articles, photographs, poems, magazines, and other various miscellany deemed by Charles Kendrick to be "worth saving."
- Maps of France, undated (Box-folder 3: 3-4)
- Travel File, 1918-1952
  Diaries, transcripts, and other documents that deal with Charles Kendrick's various trips, from serving in World War I to exploring Africa, South America, and various parts of Europe.
  - Diary of the First World War, 1918 (Box-folder 3: 5)
    Two diaries and a chronological transcript.
  - The War Front, 1944 (Box-folder 4: 1)
    Pamphlets, memoranda, newspaper articles, correspondence, writings, and various other documents.
  - South America trip, 1945 (Box-folder 4: 2)
    Notes and the transcript of a diary.
  - Diary of a trip to Africa, 1947 (Box-folder 4: 3)
    A diary and a pamphlet.
  - European Trip Diary, 1949 (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - Travel Diary of the World Tour, 1952 (Box-folder 4: 5)
- "Changing China" and "The Memoirs of Charles Kendrick,", 1942-1972 (Box-folder 4: 6)
- Organization File, 1916-1964
  Correspondence, reports, newspaper articles, and various other documents and forms of media that deal with Charles Kendrick's involvement with numerous professional and community organizations, most notably: the National Association of Manufacturers, the Hoover Institution, the San Francisco War Memorial, the Golden Gate International Exposition, and the National Industrial Conference Board.
  - Alphabetical List of Members of Exposition Committees binder, undated (Box-folder 4: 7)
    A binder of contact information for people involved in Exposition Committees (most likely the Golden Gate International Exposition).
  - California Commission on Colonization, 1916-1917 (Box-folder 5: 1)
    Reports, correspondence, and other documents relating to the California Commission on Colonization.
  - Community Chest, 1923 (Box-folder 5: 2)
    Reports, correspondence, minutes, and other documents relating to the Community Chest.
  - San Francisco War Memorial, 1923-1937
    Correspondence, reports, pamphlets, and other documents relating to the establishment of the San Francisco War Memorial.
    - 1929 (Box-folder 5: 3)
    - Correspondence, 1935 (Box-folder 5: 4)
    - Minutes, reports, memos, and other miscellaneous documents, 1935 (Box-folder 5: 5)
    - 1937 (Box-folder 5: 6)
    - War Memorial Data, 1923-1929 (Box-folder 5: 7)
  - Golden Gate International Exposition, 1938-1940
    Reports, correspondence, minutes, membership lists, pamphlets, memoranda, and other documents relating to the Golden Gate International Exposition.
    - 1938 (Box-folder 5: 8)
    - Correspondence, 1939 (Box-folder 6: 1)
    - Minutes, Reports, and Miscellaneous Documents, 1939 (Box-folder 6: 2)
    - Miscellaneous, circa 1940 (Box-folder 6: 3)
      Reports, pamphlets, guest lists, and other miscellaneous documents relating to the Golden Gate International Exposition.
  - Amendment Number 24, 1928 (Box-folder 6: 4)
    Correspondence, essays, and reports surrounding the passage of state legislature Amendment Number 24 in 1928.
  - Bohemian Club (Pacific Union Club), 1941-1945 (Box-folder 6: 5)
    Photographs, pamphlets, and reports relating to the Bohemian Club.
  - Pan American Union, circa 1942 (Box-folder 6: 6)
    Photographs, reports, newspaper articles, and other documents relating to the Pan American Union.
  - Browning Rangers, 1944-1949 (Box-folder 6: 7)
    Correspondence, reports, and notes relating to an organization known as the Browning Rangers.
  - Far East America Council, 1945-1950 (Box-folder 6: 8)
    Correspondence, pamphlets, photographs, reports, and other documents relating to the Far East America Council and a reception honoring Dr. T.V. Soong.
  - Mills College, circa 1943 (Box-folder 6: 9)
    Pamphlets, programs, and speeches that involve an address Charles Kendrick gave at a ceremony for Mills College.
  - Hetch Hetchy Water System, 1923-1925 (Box-folder 6: 10)
    Correspondence, newspaper articles, reports, and other documents concerning the Hetch Hetchy Water System.
  - National Association of Manufacturers, 1957-1961
    Reports, correspondence, pamphlets, and other documents relating to the activities of the National Association of Manufacturers.
    - Reports, lists, and other miscellaneous documents, 1957 (Box-folder 7: 1)
    - Correspondence, 1957 (Box-folder 7: 2)
    - Reports, minutes, and other miscellaneous documents, 1959 (Box-folder 7: 3)
    - Pamphlets and other media, 1959 (Box-folder 7: 4)
    - Correspondence, 1959 (Box-folder 7: 5)
    - Reports, lists, minutes, and other miscellaneous documents, 1960 (Box-folder 7: 6)
    - Correspondence, 1960 (Box-folder 7: 7)
    - 1961 (Box-folder 8: 1)
  - National Industrial Conference Board, 1957-1961
    Correspondence, reports, pamphlets, and other documents relating to the activities of the National Industrial Conference Board.
    - 1957 (Box-folder 8: 2)
    - 1959 (Box-folder 8: 3)
    - 1960 (Box-folder 8: 4)
    - 1961 (Box-folder 8: 5)
  - Hoover Institution, 1938-1964
    Correspondence, reports, newspaper articles, and other documents dealing with the activities of the Hoover Institution.
    - 1960 (Box-folder 8: 6)
    - 1961 (Box-folder 8: 7)
    - General documents, 1938-1964
      Documents that deal with Herbert Hoover and the Hoover Institution.
      - Correspondence, 1938-1960 (Box-folder 8: 8)
        Letters, telegrams, and other forms of correspondence relating to the establishment of the Hoover Institution, and various activities surrounding it between the years 1938-1960. Includes personal correspondence between Herbert Hoover and Charles Kendrick.
      - Miscellaneous documents, 1938-1964 (Box-folder 8: 9)